

Ph.D. STUDENT AT THE UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON

Paul Allen Center, 185 E Stevens Way NE AE100R, Seattle, WA 98195

C (206) 739-4801 | ■ yuchaz@uw.edu | © yuchaz.github.io | □ yuchaz | □ yuchaz

Summary_

Research Manifold learning, Geometric data analysis, Dynamic networks, Embedding.

Publications First author of 2 top-tier Machine Learning conference (NeurIPS, KDD) papers and 1 NeurIPS workshop poster.

Affiliations Institute for Pure and Applied Mathematics, Microsoft Corporation, University of Washington, National Taiwan University.

Programming Python (Advanced), MATLAB (Advanced), JavaScript (Intermediate), C++ (Intermediate).

Languages English (Professional), Mandarin (Native), Taiwanese (Native).

Education

University of Washington

Seattle, WA Sep. 2016 - PRESENT

Ph.D. IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING

National Taiwan University

Taipei, Taiwan

B.S. IN PHYSICS

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2015

Publications

· Advisor: Marina Meilă

REFERRED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **YU-CHIA CHEN** and Marina Meilă. Selecting the independent coordinates of manifolds with large aspect ratios. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 32*, pages 1086–1095, 2019
- [2] Samson J. Koelle, Hanyu Zhang, Marina Meilă and **Yu-Chia Chen**. Manifold Coordinates with Physical Meaning. *Second Workshop on Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences (NeurIPS 2019)*, Vancouver, Canada, December, 2019
- [3] **YU-CHIA CHEN**, Avleen S. Bijral, and Juan Lavista Ferres. On Dynamic Network Models and Application to Causal Impact. In *Proceedings of the 25th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery & Data Mining*, KDD '19, pages 1194–1204, Anchorage, AK, USA, 2019. ACM
- [4] **YU-CHIA CHEN**, Dominique Perrault-Joncas, Marina Meilă, and James McQueen. Improved Graph Laplacian via Geometric Self-Consistency. *NIPS Workshop on NIPS Highlights (MLTrain), Learn How to code a paper with state of the art frameworks*, Long Beach, CA, December 2017
- [5] Peifeng Jing, Kosuke Winston, **Yu-Chia Chen**, Benjamin S. Freedman, and Lih Y. Lin. Patterning and Colonizing Stem Cells with Optical Trapping. In *Optics in the Life Sciences Congress (2017), Paper OtM4E.2*, page OtM4E.2. Optical Society of America, April 2017
- [6] **YU-CHIA CHEN**, Cih-Su Wang, Tsung-Yuan Chang, Tai-Yuan Lin, Hsiu-Mei Lin, and Yang-Fang Chen. Ultraviolet and visible random lasers assisted by diatom frustules. *Optics Express*, 23(12):16224–16231, June 2015
- [7] Cih-Su Wang, Chi-Shung Liau, Tzu-Ming Sun, **Yu-Chia Chen**, Tai-Yuan Lin, and Yang-Fang Chen. Biologically inspired band-edge laser action from semiconductor with dipole-forbidden band-gap transition. *Scientific Reports*, 5:8965, March 2015

PREPRINTS/UNDER REVIEW/TECHNICAL REPORTS

- [8] Yu-Chia Chen, James McQueen, Samson J. Koelle, Marina Meilă, Stefan Chmiela and Alexandre Tkatchenko. Modern Manifold Learning Methods for MD data a step by step procedural overview. http://students.washington.edu/yuchaz/files/2020-md-manifold.pdf
- [9] Samson J. Koelle, Hanyu Zhang, Marina Meilă and Yu-CHIA CHEN. Manifold Coordinates with Physical Meaning. (Under review at JMLR)

Experience ____

Geometric Data Analysis Group (prof. Marina Meilă), University of Washington

Seattle, WA

Ph.D. Student Researcher

Apr. 2017 - PRESENT

- Selecting the independent coordinates of manifolds with large aspect ratios.
- Efficient criterion based subset selection algorithm for finding independent coordinates that produce smooth embedding.
- Paper [1] accepted to NeurIPS 2019 (acceptance rate 21.2%).
- · Fast random projection based graph Laplacian construction algorithm for large scale manifold learning.
- Manifold learning for molecular dynamics (MD) simulation data [8].

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA

Jun. 2018 - Sep. 2018 RESEARCH INTERN

- Studied large scale dynamic network model based on stochastic block model (SBM) and the extension to causal impact on temporal graphs.
- Paper [3] accepted to KDD 2019 research track (acceptance rate 14.2%).

Psychological Warfare Group, Ministry of National Defense

Taipei. Taiwan Aug. 2015 - Jul. 2016

FRONT-END SOFTWARE ENGINEER (COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE)

- · Lead engineer on cloud-based file exchanging platform, which enabled user to search, view and share streaming media.
- Technology used: JavaScript (react.js), HMTL/CSS.

Semiconductor Laboratory (prof. Yang-Fang Chen), National Taiwan University

Taipei. Taiwan

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCHER

Feb. 2014 - Jun. 2015

- Investigated bio-photonics devices with wide spectrum range [6].
- Studied Perovskite and CdTe core shell quantum dots assisted random laser in bio-inspired materials [7].

Other Experience & Course Projects

Institute for Pure & Applied Mathematics (IPAM), UCLA

Los Angeles, CA

VISITING RESEARCHER

Sep. 2019 - Dec. 2019

- Participant of the Machine Learning for Physics and the Physics of Learning long program.
- White paper: https://www.ipam.ucla.edu/news/white-paper-machine-learning-for-physics-and-the-physics-of-learning/

Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering, University of Washington

Seattle, WA

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Jan. 2017 - Dec. 2017

• Courses: Digital Signal Processing (graduate level), Devices And Circuits, Discrete Time Linear Systems, Fundamentals of Electrical Engineering.

Selfie Sensei: Convolutional Neural Network based selfie instructor

Seattle WA

COURSE PROJECT Apr. 2017 - Jun 2017

• Built and trained the Google Inception-v3 model on 40 thousand selfies collected from twitter with hashtag #selfie.

Large scale medical subject heading (MeSH) term indexing

Seattle, WA

COURSE PROJECT

Jan. 2017 - Mar. 2017

• Built a CNN trained with skipgram word2vec embedding to annotate 27k MeSH terms on 12M academic articles.

Photonics Lab, University of Washington

Seattle, WA

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sep. 2016 - Dec. 2016

Dec. 2013 - Aug. 2014

• Investigated high accuracy mass sensing using Nanostructure-enhanced laser tweezers and its application to stem cell patterning [5].

ScoreMaster Team Taipei, Taiwan

CO-FOUNDER

· Developed online tutoring platform that matched high school students and undergraduate tutors.

Honors & Awards

2019	Student Travel Award, NeurIPS 2019	Vancouver, Canada
2019	Student Travel Award, KDD 2019	Anchorage, AK
2019	Travel Grant, UW Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering	Seattle, WA
2013	Scholarship, Taipower Academic Scholarship	Taipei, Taiwan
2012	Scholarship, Taipower Academic Scholarship	Taipei, Taiwan
2010	Second prizes, Physics Scholastic Ability Contest	Kaohsiung, Taiwan

Selected Talks

Feb. 2020 Seminar Talk, UW Geometric Data Analysis Group, Hodge Laplacians on graphs.

Seattle, WA

Dec. 2019 **Poster Presentation**, NeurIPS'19, Selecting the Independent Coordinates of Manifolds with Large Aspect Ratios.

Vancouver, Canada Los Angeles, CA

Aug. 2019 Poster Presentation, KDD'19, On Dynamic Network Models and Application to Causal Impact.

Oct. 2019 Seminar Talk, IPAM, Selecting the Independent Coordinates of Manifolds with Large Aspect Ratios.

Anchorage, AK

Sep. 2018 Seminar Talk, Microsoft, On Dynamic Network Models and Application to Causal Impact.

Redmond, WA

Jan. 2018 Seminar Talk, UW Geometric Data Analysis Group, Improved Graph Laplacian via geometric self-consistency.

Seattle, WA



UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON

CSE 525 Randomized Algorithm; EE 546 Learning and Game Theory; STAT 512 Statistical Inference; STAT 548 Machine Learning for Big Data; STAT 538 Statistical Learning; CSE 599 Interplay between Convex Optimization and Geometry; MATH 515 Fundamental of Optimization; EE 576 Computer Vision; EE 595 Data Science for Sequencing; CSE 517 Natural Language Processing; EE 518 Digital Signal Processing.

NATIONAL TAIWAN UNIVERSITY (SELECTED)

PHYS 8049 Introduction to Quantum Computation & Information; PHYS 4001 Optics; PHYS 3002 Group Theory; PHYS 3001 Complex Analysis.

References_

Marina Meilă

DEPARTMENT OF STATISTICS. UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON

mmp@stat.washington.edu

Avleen S. Bijral

MICROSOFT CORPORATION

avbijral@microsoft.com

Les Atlas

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRICAL & COMPUTER ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON

atlas@u.washington.edu

Yang-Fang Chen

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, NATIONAL TAIWAN UNIVERSITY

yfchen@phys.ntu.edu.tw